<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- This file is part of the book -->
<!--                               -->
<!-- Calculus I Lab Manual         -->
<!--                               -->
<!-- Steve Simonds (author)        -->
<!-- Alex Jordan (editor)          -->

<section xml:id="section-derivative-units">
    <title>Derivative Units</title>

    <p>We can think about the instantaneous velocity as being <em>the instantaneous rate of change</em> in position. In general, whenever you see the phrase <q>rate of change</q> you can assume that the rate of change at one instant is being discussed. When we want to discuss average rates of change over a time interval we always say <q>average rate of change.</q></p>

    <p>In general, if <m>f</m> is any function, then <em><m>\fe{\fd{f}}{a}</m> tells us the rate of change in <m>f</m> at <m>a</m></em>. Additionally, if <m>f</m> is an applied function with an input unit of <m>i_{\text{unit}}</m> and an output unit of <m>f_{\text{unit}}</m>, then the unit on <m>\fe{\fd{f}}{a}</m> is <m>\frac{f_{\text{unit}}}{i_{\text{unit}}}</m>. Please note that this unit loses all meaning if it is simplified in any way. Consequently, <em>we do not simplify derivative units in any way, shape, or form</em>.</p>

    <p>For example, if <m>\fe{v}{t}</m> is the velocity of your car (measured in <quantity><unit base="mile"/><per base="hour"/></quantity>) where <m>t</m> is the amount of time that has passed since you hit the road (measured in minutes), then the unit on <m>\fe{\fd{v}}{t}</m> is <m>\frac{\text{mi}/\text{h}}{\text{min}}</m>.</p>

    <exercises>
        <exercisegroup>
            <introduction>
                <p>Determine the unit for the first derivative function for each of the following functions. Remember, <em>we do not simplify derivative units in any way, shape, or form</em>.</p> 
            </introduction>

            <exercise>
                <statement>
                    <p><m>\fe{V}{r}</m> is the volume of a sphere (measured in <quantity><unit prefix="milli" base="liter"/></quantity>) with radius <m>r</m> (measured in <quantity><unit prefix="milli" base="meter"/></quantity>).</p>
                </statement>
            </exercise>

            <exercise>
                <statement>
                    <p><m>\fe{A}{x}</m> is the area of a square (measured in <quantity><unit base="foot" exp="2"/></quantity>) with sides of length <m>x</m> (measured in <quantity><unit base="foot"/></quantity>).</p>
                </statement>
            </exercise>

            <exercise xml:id="exercise-bathtub">
                <statement>
                    <p><m>\fe{V}{t}</m> is the volume of water in a bathtub (measured in <quantity><unit base="gallon"/></quantity>) where <m>t</m> is the amount of time that has elapsed since the bathtub began to drain (measured in minutes).</p>
                </statement>
            </exercise>

            <exercise xml:id="exercise-bathtub-rate">
                <statement>
                    <p><m>\fe{R}{t}</m> is the rate at which a bathtub is draining (measured in <quantity><unit base="gallon"/><per base="minute"/></quantity>) where <m>t</m> is the amount of time that has elapsed since the bathtub began to drain (measured in minutes).</p>
                </statement>
            </exercise>

        </exercisegroup>

        <exercise>
            <statement>
                <p>Akbar was given a formula for the function described in <xref ref="exercise-bathtub"/>. Akbar did some calculations and decided that the value of <m>\fe{\fd{V}}{20}</m> was (without unit) <m>1.5</m>. Nguyen took one look at Akbar's value and said <q>that's wrong</q> What is it about Akbar's value that caused Nguyen to dismiss it as wrong?</p>
            </statement>
        </exercise>

        <exercise>
            <statement>
                <p>After a while Nguyen convinced Akbar that he was wrong, so Akbar set about doing the calculation over again. This time Akbar came up with a value of <quantity><mag>-12528</mag></quantity>. Nguyen took one look at Akbar's value and declared <q>still wrong.</q> What's the problem now?</p>
            </statement>
        </exercise>

        <exercisegroup>
            <introduction>
                <p>Consider the function described in <xref ref="exercise-bathtub-rate"/>.</p>
            </introduction>
            <exercise>
                <statement>
                    <p>What would it mean if the value of <m>\fe{R}{t}</m> was zero for all <m>t\gt0</m>?</p>
                </statement>
            </exercise>
            <exercise>
                <statement>
                    <p>What would it mean if the value of <m>\fe{\fd{R}}{t}</m> was zero for all <m>t</m> in <m>\ointerval{0}{2.25}</m>?</p>
                </statement>
            </exercise>
        </exercisegroup>
 
    </exercises>



</section>
