<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- This file is part of the book -->
<!--                               -->
<!-- Calculus I Lab Manual         -->
<!--                               -->
<!-- Steve Simonds (author)        -->
<!-- Alex Jordan (editor)          -->

<section xml:id="section-graph-features">
    <title>Graph Features</title>

    <p>Functions, derivatives, and antiderivatives have many entangled properties. For example, over intervals where the first derivative of a function is always positive, we know that the function itself is always increasing. (Do you understand why?) Many of these relationships can be expressed graphically. Consequently, it is imperative that you fully understand the meaning of some commonly used graphical expressions. These expressions are loosely defined in <xref ref="definition-graph-features"/>.</p>

    <definition xml:id="definition-graph-features">
        <title>Some Common Graphical Phrases</title>
        <statement>
            <p>These are loose, informal definitions. Technical, precise definitions can be found elsewhere.</p>
            <sidebyside>
                <paragraphs width="45%" valign="top">
                    <p><term>Positive function.</term> The vertical coordinates of points on the function are positive. A function is positive whenever its graph lies above the horizontal axis.</p>
                </paragraphs>
                <paragraphs width="45%" valign="top">
                    <p><term>Negative function.</term> The vertical coordinates of points on the function are negative. A function is negative whenever its graph lies below the horizontal axis.</p>
                </paragraphs>
            </sidebyside>
            <sidebyside>
                <paragraphs width="45%" valign="top">
                    <p><term>Increasing function.</term> The vertical coordinates of the function increase as you move along the curve from left to right. Linear functions with positive slope are always increasing.</p>
                </paragraphs>
                <paragraphs width="45%" valign="top">
                    <p><term>Decreasing function.</term> The vertical coordinates of the function decrease as you move along the curve from left to right. Linear functions with negative slope are always decreasing.</p>
                </paragraphs>
            </sidebyside>
            <sidebyside>
                <paragraphs width="45%" valign="top">
                    <p><term>Concave up function.</term> A function is concave up at <m>a</m> if the tangent line to the function at <m>a</m> lies below the curve. The bottom half of a circle is concave up.</p>
                </paragraphs>
                <paragraphs width="45%" valign="top">
                    <p><term>Concave down function.</term> A function is concave down at <m>a</m> if the tangent line to the function at <m>a</m> lies above the curve. The top half of a circle is concave down.</p>
                </paragraphs>
            </sidebyside>
        </statement>
    </definition>

    <exercises>
        <exercisegroup>
            <introduction>
                <p>Answer each of the following questions in reference to the function shown in <xref ref="figure-graph-features"/>. Each answer is an interval (or intervals) along the <m>x</m>-axis.</p> 
                <sidebyside>
                    <paragraphs valign="top">
                        <p>Use interval notation when expressing your answers. Make each interval as wide as possible; that is, do not break an interval into pieces if the interval does not need to be broken. Assume that the slope of the function is constant on <m>\ointerval{-\infty}{-5}</m>, <m>\ointerval{3}{4}</m>, and <m>\ointerval{4}{\infty}</m>.</p> 
                    </paragraphs>
                    <figure xml:id="figure-graph-features" valign="top">
                        <caption><m>y=\fe{f}{x}</m></caption>
                        <image> 
                            <description>a graph of a function whose curve has three separated components; the first component comes in from the left at y=3, completely flat, until it reaches(-5, 3); then it sharply bends downward, tracing a parabolic curve through a vertex at (-3,-1), back up to (-1,3); at (-1,3) the curve again sharply changes direction, bending down to (0,2), smoothly bending back up to (2,4) and then down to (3,3); this is the end of the first component, and there is a solid dot at (3,3); the second component is simply a straight line segment from (3,-2) to (4,-4); there are hollow dots at both endpoints; the third component of the curve is also a straight line; it starts up at (4,6), and moves downward and to the right with slope -2/3 until the curve exits the graph at about (7,4)</description>
                            <latex-image-code>
                            <![CDATA[\begin{tikzpicture}
                            \begin{axis}[]
                                \addplot[pccplot,
                                    domain=-7:-5,
                                    <-,
                                ]{3};
                                \addplot[pccplot,
                                    domain=-5:-1,
                                    -,
                                ]{(x+3)^2-1};
                                \addplot[pccplot,
                                    domain=-1:3,
                                    -,
                                ]{3-cos(90*x)};
                                \addplot[pccplot,
                                    domain=3:4,
                                    -,
                                ]{-2*(x-3)-2};
                                \addplot[pccplot,
                                    domain=4:7,
                                    ->,
                                ]{-2/3*(x-4)+6};
                                \addplot[
                                    soldot
                                ]coordinates{
                                    (3,3)
                                    (4,6)};
                                \addplot[
                                    holdot
                                ]coordinates{
                                    (3,-2)
                                    (4,-4)};
                            \end{axis}
                            \end{tikzpicture}]]>
                            </latex-image-code>
                        </image> 
                    </figure> 
                </sidebyside>
            </introduction>
            <exercise>
                <statement>
                    <p>Over what intervals is the function positive?</p>
                </statement>
            </exercise>
            <exercise>
                <statement>
                    <p>Over what intervals is the function negative?</p>
                </statement>
            </exercise>
            <exercise>
                <statement>
                    <p>Over what intervals is the function increasing?</p>
                </statement>
            </exercise>
            <exercise>
                <statement>
                    <p>Over what intervals is the function decreasing?</p>
                </statement>
            </exercise>
            <exercise>
                <statement>
                    <p>Over what intervals is the function concave up?</p>
                </statement>
            </exercise>
            <exercise>
                <statement>
                    <p>Over what intervals is the function concave down?</p>
                </statement>
            </exercise>
            <exercise>
                <statement>
                    <p>Over what intervals is the function linear?</p>
                </statement>
            </exercise>
            <exercise>
                <statement>
                    <p>Over what intervals is the function constant?</p>
                </statement>
            </exercise>
        </exercisegroup>
    </exercises>
</section>
