<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- This file is part of the book -->
<!--                               -->
<!-- Calculus I Lab Manual         -->
<!--                               -->
<!-- Steve Simonds (author)        -->
<!-- Alex Jordan (editor)          -->

<section xml:id="section-graph-features">
    <title>Graph Features</title>

    <p>Functions, derivatives, and antiderivatives have many entangled properties. For example, over intervals where the first derivative of a function is always positive, we know that the function itself is always increasing. (Do you understand why?)</p>

    <p>Many of these relationships can be expressed graphically. Consequently, it is imperative that you fully understand the meaning of some commonly used graphical expressions. These expressions are loosely defined in <xref ref="definition-graph-features"/>.</p>

    <definition xml:id="definition-graph-features">
        <title>Some Common Graphical Phrases</title>
        <statement>
            <p>These are loose, informal definitions. Technical, precise definitions can be found elsewhere.</p>

            <dl cols="2">
                <li><title>The function is positive.</title>This means that the vertical-coordinate of the point on the function is positive. As such, a function is positive whenever it lies above the horizontal axis.</li>
                <li><title>The function is increasing.</title>This means that the vertical-coordinate of the function consistently increases as you move along the curve from left to right. Linear functions with positive slope are always increasing.</li>
                <li><title>The function is concave up.</title>A function is concave up at <m>a</m> if the tangent line to the function at <m>a</m> lies below the curve. An upward opening parabola is everywhere concave up.</li> 
                <li><title>The function is negative.</title>This means that the vertical-coordinate of the point on the function is negative. As such, a function is negative whenever it lies below the horizontal axis.</li> 
                <li><title>The function is decreasing.</title>This means that the vertical-coordinate of the function consistently decreases as you move along the curve from left to right. Linear functions with negative slope are always decreasing.</li> 
                <li><title>The function is concave down.</title>A function is concave down at <m>a</m> if the tangent line to the function at <m>a</m> lies above the curve. A downward opening parabola is everywhere concave down.</li> 
            </dl> 
        </statement>
    </definition>

    <exercises>
        <exercisegroup>
            <introduction>
                <p>Answer each of the following questions in reference to the function shown in <xref ref="figure-graph-features"/>. Each answer is an interval (or intervals) along the <m>x</m>-axis. Use interval notation when expressing your answers. Make each interval as wide as possible; that is, do not break an interval into pieces if the interval does not need to be broken up. Assume that the slope of the function is constant on <m>\ointerval{-\infty}{-5}</m>, <m>\ointerval{3}{4}</m>, and <m>\ointerval{4}{\infty}</m>.</p> 

                <figure xml:id="figure-graph-features">
                    <caption><m>y=\fe{f}{x}</m></caption>
                    <image> 
                        <latex-image-code>
                        <![CDATA[\begin{tikzpicture}
                        \begin{axis}[]
                            \addplot[pccplot,
                                domain=-6.7:-5,
                                <-,
                            ]{3};
                            \addplot[pccplot,
                                domain=-5:-1,
                                -,
                            ]{(x+3)^2-1};
                            \addplot[pccplot,
                                domain=-1:3,
                                -,
                            ]{3-cos(90*x)};
                            \addplot[pccplot,
                                domain=3:4,
                                -,
                            ]{-2*(x-3)-2};
                            \addplot[pccplot,
                                domain=4:6.7,
                                ->,
                            ]{-2/3*(x-4)+6};
                            \addplot[
                                soldot
                            ]coordinates{
                                (3,3)
                                (4,6)};
                            \addplot[
                                holdot
                            ]coordinates{
                                (3,-2)
                                (4,-4)};
                        \end{axis}
                        \end{tikzpicture}]]>
                        </latex-image-code>
                    </image> 
                </figure> 
            </introduction>
            <exercise>
                <statement>
                    <p>Over what intervals is the function positive?</p>
                </statement>
            </exercise>
            <exercise>
                <statement>
                    <p>Over what intervals is the function negative?</p>
                </statement>
            </exercise>
            <exercise>
                <statement>
                    <p>Over what intervals is the function increasing?</p>
                </statement>
            </exercise>
            <exercise>
                <statement>
                    <p>Over what intervals is the function decreasing?</p>
                </statement>
            </exercise>
            <exercise>
                <statement>
                    <p>Over what intervals is the function concave up?</p>
                </statement>
            </exercise>
            <exercise>
                <statement>
                    <p>Over what intervals is the function concave down?</p>
                </statement>
            </exercise>
            <exercise>
                <statement>
                    <p>Over what intervals is the function linear?</p>
                </statement>
            </exercise>
            <exercise>
                <statement>
                    <p>Over what intervals is the function constant?</p>
                </statement>
            </exercise>
        </exercisegroup>
    </exercises>
</section>
