<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- This file is part of the book -->
<!--                               -->
<!-- Calculus I Lab Manual         -->
<!--                               -->
<!-- Steve Simonds (author)        -->
<!-- Alex Jordan (editor)          -->

<section xml:id="section-graphical-derivatives">
    <title>Graphical Derivatives</title>

    <p>Much information about a function's first derivative can be gleaned simply by looking at a graph of the function. In fact, a person with good visual skills can <q>see</q> the graph of the derivative while looking at the graph of the function. This activity focuses on helping you develop that skill.</p>

    <exercises> 
        <exercisegroup> 
            <introduction> 
                <p>A parabolic function is shown in <xref ref="figure-graphical-derivative"/>. The next several questions are in reference to that function.</p>

                <sidebyside> 
                    <figure xml:id="figure-graphical-derivative" width="40%">
                        <caption><m>y=\fe{g}{x}</m></caption>
                        <image>
                            <description>a graph of a quadratic function having the shape of a parabola; the parabola has its vertex at (1,6) and opens downward; the following points are on the parabola and are emphasized with a solid dot: (-5,-12), (-3,-2), (-1,4), (1,6), (3,4), (5,-2), and (7,-12)</description>
                            <latex-image-code>
                            <![CDATA[\begin{tikzpicture}
                            \begin{axis}[xmin=-8,xmax=8,ymin=-16,ymax=8,xtick={-6,-4,...,6}, minor xtick={-7,-6,...,7},ytick={-14,-12,-10,-8,-6,-4,2,4,6}, minor ytick={-15,-14,...,7},y post scale=1.5]
                                \addplot+[
                                    domain=-5.5:7.5,
                                    <->,
                                ]{-0.5*x^2+x+5.5};
                                \addplot[
                                    soldot
                                ]coordinates{
                                    (-5,-12)
                                    (-3,-2)
                                    (-1,4)
                                    (1,6)
                                    (3,4)
                                    (5,-2)
                                    (7,-12)};
                            \end{axis}
                            \end{tikzpicture}]]>
                            </latex-image-code>
                        </image>
                    </figure>
                    <figure xml:id="figure-graphical-derivative-plot" width="40%">
                        <caption><m>y=\fe{g}{x}</m></caption>
                        <image>
                            <description>a graph of a quadratic function having the shape of a parabola; the parabola has its vertex at (1,6) and opens downward; the plot is of the same function from the previous image, but no points are emphasized in this version</description>
                            <latex-image-code>
                            <![CDATA[\begin{tikzpicture}
                            \begin{axis}[xmin=-8,xmax=8,ymin=-16,ymax=8,xtick={-6,-4,...,6}, minor xtick={-7,-6,...,7},ytick={-14,-12,...,6}, minor ytick={-15,-14,...,7},y post scale=1.5]
                                \addplot+[
                                    domain=-5.5:7.5,
                                    <->,
                                ]{-0.5*x^2+x+5.5};
                            \end{axis}
                            \end{tikzpicture}]]>
                            </latex-image-code>
                        </image>
                    </figure>
                    <table xml:id="table-graphical-derivative">
                        <caption><m>y=\fe{\fd{g}}{x}</m></caption>
                        <tabular top="major">
                            <col halign="center"/>
                            <col halign="center"/>
                            <row bottom="medium">
                                <cell><m>x</m></cell>
                                <cell><m>y</m></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell><m>-5</m></cell>
                                <cell><m>6</m></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell><m>-3</m></cell>
                                <cell></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell><m>-1</m></cell>
                                <cell><m>2</m></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell><m>1</m></cell>
                                <cell></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell><m>3</m></cell>
                                <cell><m>-2</m></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell><m>5</m></cell>
                                <cell><m>-4</m></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell><m>7</m></cell>
                                <cell></cell>
                            </row>
                        </tabular>
                    </table>
                </sidebyside> 
            </introduction> 
            <exercise> 
                <statement> 
                    <p>Several values of <m>\fd{g}</m> are given in <xref ref="table-graphical-derivative"/>. For each given value of <m>x</m> draw a nice long line segment at the corresponding point on <m>g</m> whose slope is equal to the value of <m>\fd{g}</m>. If we think of these line segments as actual lines, what do we call the lines?</p> 
                </statement> 
            </exercise> 
            <exercise> 
                <statement> 
                    <p>What is the value of <m>\fe{\fd{g}}{1}</m>? How do you know? Enter that value into <xref ref="table-graphical-derivative"/>.</p>
                </statement>
            </exercise>
            <exercise>
                <statement>
                    <p>The function <m>g</m> is symmetric across the line <m>x=1</m>; that is, if we move equal distance to the left and right from this line the corresponding <m>y</m>-coordinates on <m>g</m> are always equal. Notice that the slopes of the tangent lines are <q>equal but opposite</q> at points that are equally removed from the axis of symmetry; this is reflected in the values of <m>\fe{\fd{g}}{-1}</m> and <m>\fe{\fd{g}}{3}</m>. Use the idea of <q>equal but opposite slope equidistant from the axis of symmetry</q> to complete <xref ref="table-graphical-derivative"/>.</p>
                </statement>
            </exercise>
            <exercise>
                <statement>
                    <p>Plot the points from <xref ref="table-graphical-derivative"/> onto <xref ref="figure-graphical-derivative-plot"/> and connect the dots. Determine the formula for the resultant linear function.</p>
                </statement>
            </exercise>
            <exercise>
                <statement>
                    <p>The formula for <m>\fe{g}{x}</m> is <m>-0.5x^2+x+5.5</m>. Use <xref ref="definition-first-derivative"/> to determine the formula for <m>\fe{\fd{g}}{x}</m>.</p>
                </statement>
            </exercise>
            <exercise>
                <statement>
                    <p>The line you drew onto <xref ref="figure-graphical-derivative-plot"/> is <em>not</em> a tangent line to <m>g</m>. Just what exactly is this line?</p>
                </statement>
            </exercise>
        </exercisegroup> 
        <exercisegroup> 
            <introduction> 
                <p>A function <m>f</m> is shown in <xref ref="figure-cubic"/> and the corresponding first derivative function <m>\fd{f}</m> is shown in <xref ref="figure-cubic-derivative"/>. Answer each of the following questions referencing these two functions.</p>
                <sidebyside>
                    <figure xml:id="figure-cubic" valign="top">
                        <caption><m>y=\fe{f}{x}</m></caption>
                        <image>
                            <description>the graph of a function; the curve enters from below at about (-4.2,-7), heading slightly to the right as it mainly moves upward; near (-2.5,6), the curve bends by a lot, smoothly, until it reaches about (-2,6.2), at which point the curve turns around and begins moving predominantly downward and to the right; it passes through (0,1); as it reaches about (1.5,-4), the curve bends by a lot, smoothly, so that it reaches about (2,-4.2) and turns around again; from here it moves predominantly upward and to the right, passing through (3,-2), and exiting the graph at about (4,7)</description>
                            <latex-image-code>
                            <![CDATA[\begin{tikzpicture}
                            \begin{axis}[samples=50]
                                \addplot+[
                                    domain=-4.2:4,
                                    <->,
                                ]{x^3/3-4*x+1};
                                \addplot[
                                    soldot
                                ]coordinates{
                                    (-2,6.33333)
                                    (0,1)
                                    (3,-2)};
                            \end{axis}
                            \end{tikzpicture}]]>
                            </latex-image-code>
                        </image>
                    </figure>
                    <figure xml:id="figure-cubic-derivative" valign="top">
                        <caption><m>y=\fe{\fd{f}}{x}</m></caption>
                        <image>
                            <description>the graph of a function; the overall appearance resembles a parabola, although there is no solid evidence that it is a true parabola; the curve enters from above at about (-3.5,7), moving mostly downward and slightly to the right; as it moves downward, it tapers more and more, passing through -2 on the x-axis, and then smoothly flattening out at -4 on the y-axis; then the curve bends upward, bending more and more upward as it moves to the right; it passes through (3,5); it exits the graph at about (3.5,7)</description>
                            <latex-image-code>
                            <![CDATA[\begin{tikzpicture}
                            \begin{axis}[]
                                \addplot+[
                                    domain=-3.3:3.3,
                                    <->,
                                ]{x^2-4};
                                \addplot[
                                    soldot
                                ]coordinates{
                                    (-2,0)
                                    (0,-4)
                                    (3,5)};
                            \end{axis}
                            \end{tikzpicture}]]>
                            </latex-image-code>
                        </image>
                    </figure>
                </sidebyside>
            </introduction>
            <exercise>
                <statement>
                    <p>Draw the tangent line to <m>f</m> at the three points indicated in <xref ref="figure-cubic"/> after first using the graph of <m>\fd{f}</m> to determine the exact slope of the respective tangent lines.</p>
                </statement>
            </exercise>
            <exercise>
                <statement>
                    <p>Write a sentence relating the slope of the tangent line to <m>f</m> with the corresponding <m>y</m>-coordinate on <m>\fd{f}</m>.</p>
                </statement>
            </exercise>
            <exercise>
                <statement>
                    <p>Copy each of the following sentences onto your paper and supply the words or phrases that correctly complete each sentence.</p>
                    <ul>
                        <li><p>Over the interval where <m>\fd{f}</m> is negative, <m>f</m> is <ellipsis/></p></li> 
                        <li><p>Over the interval where <m>\fd{f}</m> is positive, <m>f</m> is <ellipsis/></p></li> 
                        <li><p>Over the interval where <m>\fd{f}</m> is increasing, <m>f</m> is <ellipsis/></p></li> 
                        <li><p>Over the interval where <m>\fd{f}</m> is decreasing, <m>f</m> is <ellipsis/></p></li>
                    </ul>
                </statement>
            </exercise> 
        </exercisegroup> 
        <exercise>
            <statement>
                <p>In each of <xref autoname="plural" ref="figure-sine"/> and <xref autoname="no" ref="figure-rational"/> a function (the solid curve) is given; both of these functions are symmetric about the <m>y</m>-axis. The first derivative of each function (the dash-dotted curves) have been drawn over the interval <m>\ointerval{0}{7}</m>. Use the given portion of the first derivative together with the symmetry of the function to help you draw each first derivative over the interval <m>\ointerval{-7}{0}</m>. Please note that a function that is symmetric across a vertical line has a first derivative that is symmetric about a point.  Similarly, a function that is symmetric about a point has a first derivative that is symmetric across a vertical line.</p>
                <sidebyside>
                    <figure xml:id="figure-sine">
                        <caption><m>y=\fe{f}{x}</m> and part of the curve <m>y=\fe{\fd{f}}{x}</m></caption>
                        <image>
                            <description>the graph of two functions; the first is identified as y=g(x), and it has an overall appearance of a sinusoidal wave; the curve enters from the left, reaching a low point at (-6,2), then a high point at (-3,6), then a low point at (0,2), then a high point at (3,6), then a low point at (6,2), and then it exits the graph to the right; a second curve is on the same graph, and is denoted y=g'(x); this curve is only partially plotted; only the portion on the right half of the graph is plotted; this curve also appears to have a sinusoidal shape; the part we see abruptly starts at (0,0), moving up to a peak at (1.5,2), then down to a low point at (4.5,2), then upward exiting the graph at about (7,1.5)</description> 
                            <latex-image-code>
                            <![CDATA[\begin{tikzpicture}
                            \begin{axis}[legend style={at={(1,0)},anchor=south east},legend entries={$y=\fe{g}{x}$,$y=\fe{\fd{g}}{x}$},samples=50,]
                                \addplot+[
                                    domain=-6.8:6.8,
                                    <->,
                                ]{4-2*cos(x*60)};
                                \addplot+[
                                    domain=0:6.8,
                                    ->,
                                ]{2*sin(x*60)};
                            \end{axis}
                            \end{tikzpicture}]]>
                            </latex-image-code>
                        </image>
                    </figure>
                    <figure xml:id="figure-rational" >
                        <caption><m>y=\fe{f}{x}</m> and part of the curve <m>y=\fe{\fd{f}}{x}</m></caption>
                        <image>
                            <description>the graph of two functions; the first is identified as y=g(x); it enters the graph from the left at about (-7,3.5), moving downward and to the right with an almost constant slope; it reaches about (-1,1) and smoothly bends upward so that it becomes almost vertical; the curve exits the graph at about (-0.3,7); a second portion of this same curve comes in on the right half of the graph, symmetrically to the first portion; it comes in from the top at about (0.3,7), moves mostly downward and ever so slightly to the right until reaching about (1,1), where it smoothly bends so that it continues moving upward and to the right, with a seemingly constant slop until it exits the graph at about (7,3.5); a second curve is identified as y=g'(x); only the portion on the right half of the graph is plotted; this portion enters the graph from below at about (0.2,-7), moves mostly upward to (1,0), where it bends smoothly, so that it continues moving mostly rightward, becoming closer and closer to the horizontal line y=1/2; this portion of the curve exits the graph at about (7,1/2)</description>
                            <latex-image-code>
                            <![CDATA[\begin{tikzpicture}
                            \begin{axis}[legend style={at={(1,0)},anchor=south east},legend entries={$y=\fe{g}{x}$,$y=\fe{\fd{g}}{x}$}]
                                \addplot+[
                                    variable=t,
                                    domain=0:32.75,
                                ]({-0.2998*1.1^t},{(0.2998*1.1^t)/2+1/(6*(0.2998*1.1^t)^3)+1/6});
                                \addplot+[
                                    variable=t,
                                    domain=0:33.957,
                                ]({0.26726*1.1^t},{1/2-1/(2*(0.26726*1.1^t)^2)});
                                \addplot+[asymptote,
                                    domain=7:-7,
                                ]{1/2} node[above right] {$y=1/2$};
                                \addplot+[
                                    variable=t,
                                    domain=0:32.75,
                                ]({0.2998*1.1^t},{(0.2998*1.1^t)/2+1/(6*(0.2998*1.1^t)^3)+1/6});
                            \end{axis}
                            \end{tikzpicture}]]>
                            </latex-image-code>
                        </image>
                    </figure>
                </sidebyside>
            </statement>
        </exercise>
        <exercisegroup>
            <introduction>
                <p>A graph of the function <m>f</m> given by <m>\fe{f}{x}=\frac{1}{x}</m> is shown in <xref ref="figure-one-over-x"/>.</p>
                <sidebyside>
                    <figure xml:id="figure-one-over-x" >
                        <caption><m>y=\fe{f}{x}=\frac{1}{x}</m></caption>
                        <image>
                            <description>a graph of a function whose curve has two portions; the first portion enters from the left, only a small bit below the x-axis; as it travels to the right, it slowly moves more and more downward; at about (-1,-1), it bends much more downward, moving almost vertically downward and exiting the graph a bit to the left of the y-axis; the second portion is a symmetric opposite from the first; the second portion enters the graph from the top, just to the right of the y-axis; it moves mostly straight down and slightly to the right, until at about (1,1) it smoothly bends rightward; it continues moving rightward, moving slightly downard too, until it leaves the graph on the right side slightly above the x-axis</description> 
                            <latex-image-code>
                            <![CDATA[\begin{tikzpicture}
                            \begin{axis}[]
                                \addplot[pccplot,
                                    variable=t,
                                    domain=0:39.278,
                                    <->,
                                ]({-1/6.5*1.1^t},{1/(-1/6.5*1.1^t)});
                                \addplot[pccplot,
                                    variable=t,
                                    domain=0:39.278,
                                    <->,
                                ]({1/6.5*1.1^t},{1/(1/6.5*1.1^t)});
                                \addplot+[asymptote,
                                    domain=7:-7,
                                ]{0} node[above right] {$y=0$};
                                \addplot+[asymptote,
                                ] coordinates {(0,7) (0,-7)} node[above right] {\rotatebox{90}{$x=0$}};
                            \end{axis}
                            \end{tikzpicture}]]>
                            </latex-image-code>
                        </image>
                    </figure>
                     <figure xml:id="figure-derivative-of-one-over-x" >
                        <caption><m>y=\fe{\fd{f}}{x}</m></caption>
                        <image>
                            <description>a blank graph, with x-axis and y-axis each ranging from -7 to 7</description>
                            <latex-image-code>
                            <![CDATA[\begin{tikzpicture}
                            \begin{axis}[]
                            \end{axis}
                            \end{tikzpicture}]]>
                            </latex-image-code>
                        </image>
                    </figure>
                </sidebyside>
            </introduction>
            <exercise xml:id="exercise-negative-derivative-of-one-over-x">
                <statement>
                    <p>Except at <m>0</m>, there is something that is always true about the value of <m>\fd{f}</m>; what is the common trait?</p> 
                </statement>
            </exercise>
            <exercise xml:id="exercise-derivative-of-one-over-x">
                <statement>
                    <p>Use <xref ref="definition-first-derivative"/> to find the formula for <m>\fe{\fd{f}}{x}</m>.</p>
                </statement>
            </exercise>
            <exercise>
                <statement>
                    <p>Does the formula for <m>\fe{\fd{f}}{x}</m> support your answer to <xref ref="exercise-negative-derivative-of-one-over-x"/>?</p>
                </statement>
            </exercise>
            <exercise xml:id="exercise-asymptotes-one-over-x">
                <statement>
                    <p>Use the formula for <m>\fe{\fd{f}}{x}</m> to determine the horizontal and vertical asymptotes to the graph of <m>y=\fe{\fd{f}}{x}</m>.</p>
                </statement>
            </exercise>
            <exercise>
                <statement>
                    <p>Keeping it simple, draw onto <xref ref="figure-derivative-of-one-over-x"/> a curve with the asymptotes found in <xref ref="exercise-asymptotes-one-over-x"/> and the property determined in <xref ref="exercise-negative-derivative-of-one-over-x"/>. Does the curve you drew have the properties you would expect to see in the first derivative of <m>f</m>? For example, <m>f</m> is concave down over <m>\ointerval{-\infty}{0}</m>, and concave up over <m>\ointerval{0}{\infty}</m>; what are the corresponding differences in the behavior of <m>\fd{f}</m> over those two intervals?</p>
                </statement>
            </exercise> 
        </exercisegroup>
        <exercise>
            <statement>
                <p>A graph of the function <m>g</m> is shown in <xref ref="figure-arctangent"/>. The absolute minimum value ever obtained by <m>\fd{g}</m> is <m>-3</m>. With that in mind, draw <m>\fd{g}</m> onto <xref ref="figure-derivative-of-arctangent"/>. Make sure that you draw and label any and all necessary asymptotes. Please note that <m>g</m> is symmetric about the point <m>\point{1}{2}</m>.</p>
                <sidebyside>
                    <figure xml:id="figure-arctangent" >
                        <caption><m>y=\fe{g}{x}</m></caption>
                        <image>
                            <description>a grpah of a function that enters from the left just below y=5; the curve moves rightward fairly flat, but begins to move more and more downward as well; it reaches its steepest downward point at (1,2), and then continues to move right, but bends less and less downward; by the time it reaches the right edge of the graph, it is essentially horizontal, and exits the graph just above the line y=-1</description>
                            <latex-image-code>
                            <![CDATA[\begin{tikzpicture}
                            \begin{axis}[]
                                \addplot+[smooth,
                                    domain=-6.8:6.8,
                                ]{2-atan((x-1)*sqrt(3))/30};
                                \addplot[asymptote,
                                    domain=0:-7,
                                    ->,
                                ]{5} node[above right] {$y=5$};
                                \addplot[asymptote,
                                    domain=0:7,
                                    ->,
                                ]{-1} node[below left] {$y=-1$};
                            \end{axis}
                            \end{tikzpicture}]]>
                            </latex-image-code>
                        </image>
                    </figure>
                    <figure xml:id="figure-derivative-of-arctangent" >
                        <caption><m>y=\fe{\fd{g}}{x}</m></caption>
                        <image>
                            <description>a blank graph, with x-axis and y-axis each ranging from -7 to 7</description>
                            <latex-image-code>
                            <![CDATA[\begin{tikzpicture}
                            \begin{axis}[]
                            \end{axis}
                            \end{tikzpicture}]]>
                            </latex-image-code>
                        </image>
                    </figure>
                </sidebyside>
            </statement>
        </exercise>

        <exercisegroup>
            <introduction>
                <p>Answer the following questions in reference to the function <m>w</m>, shown in <xref ref="figure-inflection-points"/>.</p>
                <figure xml:id="figure-inflection-points" valign="top" width="90%">
                    <caption><m>y=\fe{w}{x}</m></caption>
                    <image>
                        <description>a graph with x-axis ranging from -1 to 10, and y-axis ranging from -1 to 10; the curve enters from below, slightly to the left of the y-axis; it passes through the origin, and continues moving mostly upward for a while; but it bends more and more to the right, until it reaches about (2,5.1), where it temporarily appears to be flat; then it bends a little upward briefly, flattening out again at about (4,5.5); now the curve turns downward as it keeps traveling to the right; it eventually reaches a low point at about (7,0.7), where it smoothly turns around and travels predominantly upwards and slightly to the right; the curve exits the graph at about (8.3,10)</description>
                        <latex-image-code>
                        <![CDATA[\begin{tikzpicture}
                        \begin{axis}[width=0.75\textwidth,xmin=-1,xmax=10,ymin=-1,ymax=10,xtick={-1,0,...,10}, minor xtick={-1,-0.5,...,10},ytick={-1,0,...,10}, minor ytick={-1,-0.5,...,10},grid=major,samples=100]
                            \addplot+[
                                domain=-0.1:8.25,
                                <->,
                            ]{x^5/60-5/16*x^4+19/9*x^3-13/2*x^2+28/3*x};
                        \end{axis}
                        \end{tikzpicture}]]>
                        </latex-image-code>
                    </image>
                </figure>
            </introduction>

            <exercise>
                <statement>
                    <p> An <term>inflection point</term> is a point where the function is continuous and the concavity of the function changes. The inflection points on <m>w</m> occur at <m>2</m>, <m>3.25</m>, and <m>6</m>. With that in mind, over each interval stated in <xref ref="table-inflection-points"/> exactly two of the properties from its caption apply to <m>\fd{w}</m>. Complete <xref ref="table-inflection-points"/> with the appropriate pairs of properties.</p> 
                    <table xml:id="table-inflection-points">
                        <caption>Properties of <m>\fd{w}</m> (positive, negative, increasing, or decreasing)</caption>
                        <tabular top="major">
                            <col halign="center"/>
                            <col halign="center"/>
                            <row bottom="medium">
                                <cell>Interval</cell>
                                <cell>Properties of <m>\fd{w}</m></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row bottom="minor">
                                <cell><m>\ointerval{-\infty}{2}</m></cell>
                                <cell><m>\phantom{\text{positive/negative, increasing/decreasing}}</m></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row bottom="minor">
                                <cell><m>\ointerval{2}{3.25}</m></cell>
                                <cell />
                            </row>
                            <row bottom="minor">
                                <cell><m>\ointerval{3.25}{4}</m></cell>
                                <cell />
                            </row>
                            <row bottom="minor">
                                <cell><m>\ointerval{4}{6}</m></cell>
                                <cell />
                            </row>
                            <row bottom="minor">
                                <cell><m>\ointerval{6}{7}</m></cell>
                                <cell />
                            </row>
                            <row bottom="minor">
                                <cell><m>\ointerval{7}{\infty}</m></cell>
                                <cell />
                            </row>
                        </tabular>
                    </table>
                </statement>
            </exercise>
            <exercise>
                <statement>
                    <p>In <xref ref="table-values-for-w-prime"/>, three possible values are given for <m>\fd{w}</m> at several values of <m>x</m>. In each case, one of the values is correct. Use tangent lines to <m>w</m> to determine each of the correct values.</p>
                    <sidebyside>
                        <table xml:id="table-values-for-w-prime" >
                            <caption>Choose the correct values for <m>\fd{w}</m></caption>
                            <tabular top="major">
                                <col halign="center"/>
                                <col halign="center"/>
                                <row bottom="medium">
                                    <cell><m>x</m></cell>
                                    <cell>Proposed values</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell><m>0</m></cell>
                                    <cell><m>\sfrac{2}{3}</m> or <m>\sfrac{8}{3}</m> or <m>\sfrac{28}{3}</m></cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell><m>1</m></cell>
                                    <cell><m>\sfrac{1}{2}</m> or <m>\sfrac{3}{2}</m> or <m>\sfrac{5}{2}</m></cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell><m>3</m></cell>
                                    <cell><m>\sfrac{1}{3}</m> or <m>1</m> or <m>3</m></cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell><m>5</m></cell>
                                    <cell><m>-\sfrac{1}{2}</m> or <m>-1</m> or <m>-\sfrac{3}{2}</m></cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell><m>6</m></cell>
                                    <cell><m>-\sfrac{4}{3}</m> or <m>-\sfrac{8}{3}</m> or <m>-4</m></cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell><m>8</m></cell>
                                    <cell><m>1</m> or <m>6</m> or <m>12</m></cell>
                                </row>
                            </tabular>
                        </table>
                        <figure xml:id="figure-w-prime" >
                            <caption><m>y=\fe{\fd{w}}{x}</m></caption>
                            <image>
                                <description>a blank graph, with x-axis ranging from -1 to 10, and y-axis ranging from -12 to 12</description>
                                <latex-image-code>
                                <![CDATA[\begin{tikzpicture}
                                \begin{axis}[xmin=-1,xmax=10,ymin=-12,ymax=12,xtick={0,1,...,10}, minor xtick={-1,0,...,10},ytick={-12,-11,...,12}, minor ytick={-12,-11,...,12},y post scale=2.4]
                                \end{axis}
                                \end{tikzpicture}]]>
                                </latex-image-code>
                            </image>
                        </figure> 
                    </sidebyside>
                </statement>
            </exercise>
            <exercise>
                <statement>
                    <p>The value of <m>\fd{w}</m> is the same at <m>2</m>, <m>4</m>, and <m>7</m>. What is this common value?</p>
                </statement>
            </exercise>
            <exercise>
                <statement>
                    <p>Put it all together and draw <m>\fd{w}</m> onto <xref ref="figure-w-prime"/>.</p>
                </statement>
            </exercise>
        </exercisegroup>

    </exercises> 
</section>
